Guide to the Maxine Kumin Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- January 2005 Acquisition, 1969-2004; 5.63; (11 boxes)
  - Audiovisual Material
    - Video Recordings
      - Four interviews with Maxine Kumin, 1986-1994; YCALMSS734_0003; 1; 01:48:35 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002102338978)
        Chronicle, 1986 January 30, Maxine's interview, about 30 minutes (5 minutes Maxine); WH Crossroads 1990 May 25, Maxine interview, about 30 minutes (5-10 minutes Maxine); Judith in ABC interview Fr. Belgrade 1992 May 19/David Carroll Chronicle 1994 May 25
      - "Poetry Live 204, Maxine Kumin/James Applewhite" UNC Center for Public Television, 1997 April 3; YCALMSS734_0004; 1; 00:27:33 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002102338986)
      - "The Writing Life, Horsing Around with Poets Maxine Kumin and Henry Taylor" produced by the Howard County Poetry and Literature Society, Columbia, Maryland, 1997 September 29; YCALMSS734_0005; 1; 00:30:32 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002102338994)
      - "The Writing Life, Henry Taylor Hosts MK" produced by the Howard County Poetry and Literature Society, Columbia, Maryland, 1997 September 29; YCALMSS734_0006; 1; 00:30:38 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002102339000)
      - "Chronicle, MK interview; Victor Kumin interview", 2000-2001; YCALMSS734_0007; 1; 00:55:14 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002102339059)
      - "Frontiers of Knowledge, Maxine Kumin", 2001 December 2; YCALMSS734_0008; 1; 00:59:01 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002102339026)
      - "Yankee Cable Network, Kearsarge Valley Magazine, Interview with MK", 2002 October 8; YCALMSS734_0009; 1; 00:30:59 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002102339034)
      - "North of Boston: Readings by NH Poets, Jane Kenyon, Donald Hall, Maxine Kumin, Charles Simic", undated; YCALMSS734_0010; 1; 02:27:44 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002102339042)
  - Computer media
    - M. W. Kumin BACKUP 1-24-04, 2005-ycal-0105-a-0001; 1 (Box 47)
      Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- August 2006 Acquisition, 1974-2005; 3.92; (7 boxes)
  The August 2006 Acquisition contains correspondence, writings, printed material, personal papers, and sound and video recordings. There are large files of drafts and proofs of Selected Poems 1960-1990 (1997), Always Beginning (2000), Quit Monks or Die (1999), and Jack and Other New Poems (2005). Additional professional materials relate to speaking engagements, recommendations, and awards, such as honorary degrees. There are also sound and video recordings of Kumin readings and other activities.
  Box 54 (sound and video recordings, computer disk): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 899.
  Purchased from James S. Jaffe on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 2006.
  - Selected Poems 1960-1990, master galley, 1996 (Box 48)
  - Selected Poems 1960-1990, additional papers with corrections, 1996 (Box 48)
  - Selected Poems 1960-1990, master galley proofs, 1996; 2 (Box 48)
  - Selected Poems 1960-1990, typescript, corrected, 1996; 2 (Box 48)
  - Selected Poems 1960-1990, final galley proofs, 1996; 2 (Box 48)
  - "Audience," typescript, undated (Box 48)
  - Always Beginning, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 48)
  - Always Beginning, galley proof, 2000; 2 (Box 48)
  - Quit Monks or Die, typescript, undated (Box 48)
  - Quit Monks or Die, corrections, undated; 2 (Box 48)
  - Quit Monks or Die, typescript, undated; 3 (Box 48)
  - Poems, 1999-2000 (Box 49)
  - Family letters, 1986-1991, undated (Box 49)
  - Students -- would-be writers, 1998-2004 (Box 49)
  - Miscellaneous magazines, 2002-2003 (Box 49)
  - Miscellaneous presses, 1998-2003 (Box 49)
  - Speaking completed, 2002-2004, undated (Box 49)
  - Cogging, rabies, registration etc., 1974-1991 (Box 49)
  - Sequel, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 49)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 49)
  - Hand-colored drawings, undated (Box 49)
  - Poems, 2000-2001 (Box 49)
  - Reprints, permissions, anthologies, 2001-2003 (Box 49)
  - Recommendations, blurbs, tenure review, 2002-2003 (Box 49)
  - Poems more, 2004, undated (Box 49)
  - Poems, 2001 (Box 49)
  - Requests miscellaneous, 1997-2004 (Box 49)
  - Publicity, 1998-2005 (Box 49)
  - Flyers, posters, prospectus, 1999-2002 (Box 49)
  - Animal rights, lecture notes, 1999 (Box 49)
  - Essays about MK, 1994, undated; 2 (Box 50)
  - Worksheets - miscellaneous, 2004, undated (Box 50)
  - Letters from writers, 1998-2004; 11 (Box 50)
  - Jack and Other New Poems, original typescript, undated (Box 50)
  - Jack and Other New Poems, 2nd pass proofs, 2004 July 8 (Box 50)
  - Jack and Other New Poems, 1st pass master proof, 2004 July 8 (Box 50)
  - Jack and Other New Poems, 2004 July 8 (Box 50)
  - Jack and Other New Poems, photocopy of original typescript, undated (Box 50)
  - Jack and Other New Poems, corrected typescript, undated (Box 50)
  - Jack and Other New Poems, miscellaneous corrected pages, 2004 August 16 (Box 50)
  - Jack and Other New Poems, corrected page proofs, 2004 (Box 50)
  - Copper Canyon Press, 1998-2001 (Box 50)
  - Old worksheets, 1991-1997 (Box 50)
  - Fans and casual friends, 2002 (Box 50)
  - Proposed sequel to Quit Monks or Die, undated (Box 50)
  - Deductibles, 2004 (Box 50)
  - Commercially released CDs
    - "The Writer's Almanac", 2005; (3 compact discs) (Box 51)
    - "The Exchange, Maxine Kumin", 2005 September 23 (Box 51)
    - "The Front Porch, Maxine Kumin", 2005 April 11 (Box 51)
    - "Idyllwild Arts, Summer Poetry Program", 2005 (Box 51)
    - "New England College, Faculty Lectures", 2003; (2 compact discs) (Box 51)
    - "Maxine Kumin, Paradoxical Freedom in Writing in Form", 2003 June (Box 51)
    - "Poetry Reading by Maxine Kumin", 2003 June (Box 51)
    - "Maxine Kumin, The Sestina", 2004 June (Box 51)
    - "Nuts & Bolts: Blank Verse and Open Forms, Maxine Kumin, Gerald Stern, and Joan Larkin", 2004 June (Box 51)
  - Audiovisual material, non-commercial
    - "Yale Collegium Musicum", 2003 October 1; (1 compact disc)
      Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services
      2006-ycal-1163-0001
    - "Mina, Maxine, Marianne ... and More, Yale Collegium Musicum at the Beinecke Library", 2003 October 1; (1 compact disc)
      2006-ycal-1163-0002
    - "Idyllwild Arts, Summer Poetry Mini Festival", 2005 July 19; (1 DVD-R)
      2006-ycal-1163-0003
    - "Idyllwild Arts, Summer Poetry Festival, Vol. 1-2", 2005 July 23; (2 DVD-R)
      2006-ycal-1163-0004 - 2006-ycal-1163-0005
    - "Maxine Kumin. B/U", 2004 November 28; (1 computer disk)
      Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services
      2006-ycal-1163-0006
  - Awards, 1983-1996 (Box 52)
  - Regis College Honorary Degree, 1979 May 17 (Box 52)
  - Daily planner, 1979 (Box 52)
  - Calendar, 2003 (Box 52)
  - Honors presented at Harvard, undated (Box 53)
  - Honors presented at Radcliffe, 1978 June 10 (Box 53)
  - Honors presented by the State of New Hampshire, 1983-2002 (Box 53)
  - Honors presented by the City of Austin, 1980 (Box 53)
  - Prints, undated (Box 53)
  - "Memories of New England for Mezzo-soprano with Instrumental Accompaniment," music by Winifred Hyson, 1975 April (Box 53)
- January 2012 Acquisition, 1960-2011; 5.46; (11 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Writings, Other Papers, and Audiovisual Material.
  The January 2012 Acquisition contains writings, other papers, and audiovisual material. Writings include drafts and other materials relating to books published from the late 1990s onward. Other papers include correspondence, printed materials, financial and legal records, material documenting Kumin's professional and public engagements, and personal papers. Audiovisual materials document readings by Kumin and other cultural events.
  Boxes 61, 64-65 (sound and video recordings, computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Boxes 62-63 (sound recordings): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Purchased from James S. Jaffe on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 2012.
  - Writings
    - Selected Poems 1960-1990, dust jacket, 1997 (Box 55)
    - Connecting the Dots, broadside, undated (Box 55)
    - William Stafford; "Any Morning", 1998 (Box 55)
    - "Update to Autobiography in Contemporary Authors", circa 1997 (Box 55)
    - Lizzie, undated; 2 (Box 55)
    - Lofty Dogmas: Poets on Poetics, undated (Box 55)
    - The Long Marriage, dust jacket, undated (Box 55)
    - Mites to Mastodons, 2005-2006 (Box 55)
    - Quit Monks or Die, 1998-1999, undated (Box 55)
    - The Roots of Things, 2008, undated; 4 (Box 55)
    - Still to Mow, 2005-2010, undated; 8 (Box 55)
    - Very old worksheets -- poems-newly, undated (Box 55)
    - "What Color Is Caesar?", undated; 3 (Box 55)
    - Where I Live, circa 2010; 2 (Box 55)
    - The Wonderful Babies of 1809 and Other Years, 2005-2006; 2 (Box 55)
  - Other Papers
    - Calendars, 2005-2006 (Box 56)
    - Deductibles, 2005-2006 (Box 56)
    - Two engravings by Barry Moser, 2007, undated (Box 56)
    - Family, 1999-2005 (Box 56)
    - Fans & casual friends, 2005-2009; 3 (Box 56)
    - Farm - personal - medical, 2001-2002 (Box 56)
    - Friends, non-poets, 2003-2005; 3 (Box 56)
    - Friends, old, non-poets, 2005-2006; 2 (Box 56)
    - Flyers, programs and ephemera relating to speaking engagements and contributions, 1997-2010; 2 (Box 56)
    - Income, 1968-2009; 6 (Box 56)
    - Photocopies of letters from Maxine Kumin to Anne Sexton, 1960s-1970s (Box 56)
    - Lectures, 2006-2008, undated (Box 56)
    - Material related to speaking engagements, 1999-2001 (Box 56)
    - Miscellaneous magazines, 2003-2011; 3 (Box 57)
    - Miscellaneous presses, 2005-2010; 2 (Box 57)
    - Norton, 2003-2008; 2 (Box 57)
    - Old lectures, 1999-2005 (Box 57)
    - Prairie Schooner, vol. 28, nos. 1-2, 2008 (Box 57)
    - Publicity, 2005-2007 (Box 57)
    - Recommendations, blurbs, tenure reviews, etc., 1973-2010; 2 (Box 57)
    - Reprints, permissions, anthologies, 2004-2006 (Box 57)
    - Requests for interviews, 2009-2010 (Box 57)
    - Requests miscellaneous '05, 2004-2010 (Box 57)
    - Reprints, permissions, anthologies '07, 2007-2010 (Box 57)
    - Serving as judge, 2001-2010 (Box 57)
    - Speaking completed, 2004-2007; 7 (Box 57)
    - Speaking -- No -- 2001, 2001-2010 (Box 58)
    - Students & would-be writers from speaking engagements, 2005-2010 (Box 58)
    - Tear sheets -- articles & poems, etc., 1998 (Box 58)
    - To celebrate the publication of In Deep, 1987 November 7 (Box 58)
    - Writers '05-'06, 2005-2007; 2 (Box 58)
    - Writers '08, 2008-2009; 2 (Box 59)
    - Writers '10, 2010 (Box 59)
    - Selected Poems, 1960-1990, cover design, undated (Box 60)
    - "Women and Horses", "Nurture", "Getting Through", 1984-2004 (Box 60)
    - State of New Hampshire, commendation, 2010 (Box 60)
    - The Commonwealth of Massachusetts, commendation, 1973 (Box 60)
      Includes photographs and drawings
    - The Chicago Tribune (2 copies), 2008 May 30 (Box 60)
    - Mites to Mastodons, proofs, 2006 (Box 60)
    - The Writer's Chronicle, vol. 43, no. 3, 2010 December (Box 60)
    - "Five Versions of a Poem" by Marianne Moore, 2008 (Box 60)
    - Public Poetry Project poster, 2010 (Box 60)
    - Photograph of the Palace Square in Saint Petersburg, Russia, 2008 (Box 60)
    - Electronic files, 1997-2005, undated; (25 computer disks) (Box 65)
      2012-ycal-6-0001 - 2012-ycal-6-0025
  - Audiovisual Material
    - Reel-to-Reel Tapes
      - "Family Anniversary", 1965 June 29; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248212)
      - "Old Version: Urban Engineering", Master Mix II, copy, 1971 September 2; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248220)
      - Maxine Kumin, "Tape of Interview", Tel Aviv Broadcast, 1974 November; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248238)
      - CTM, "Urban Engineering", undated; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248253)
        Annotation reads: Unpulsed, bad music at the end.
      - "Memories of New England", undated; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248246)
      - "Poetry Session", Hayden Library Lounge at M.I.T., 1962 March 13; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248261)
        Poets included in the session are listed.
        Samuel Alberts
        Anne Sexton
        Maxine Kumin
        John Holmes
      - Maxine Kumin, "Reading at Breadloaf", 1969; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248279)
      - "Transformations", opera by Anne Sexton and Conrad Susa, undated; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248287)
        Contents of this audiotape reel are listed.
        Side 1 / Side 2
        "The Gold Key"
        "Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs"
        "The White Snake"
        "Iron Hans"
        "Rumpelstiltskin"
        "Rapunzel"
        "Godfather Death"
        "The Wonderful Musician"
        "Hansel and Gretel"
        "Briar Rose"
        There is a letter included with this audiotape reel. It reads: "Dear Max, So finally here 'tis. I had it reproduced by a professional recording company in its entirety, just as I had taped it originally off the radio. So you'll get not only the opera itself, but tid-bits of "This is KPFA-KPFB Berkeley", etc., not to mention an interview between the two sections of the opera between a Dennis somebody and Phillip Brunel, complete with scattering of vapid remarks, but, also, some not so vapid discussion of the muicality, rhythms, Susa found inherent in Anne's poetry. As I recall, Anne told me she and Susa had not discussed the question of musical rhythms, ever, as applicable to the content of the poetry, & found some of same uncanny in their rightness; e.g., the almost bossa nova rhythm of the introductory passage of "Rapunzel", not to mention other instances throughout the work. Just who the guy is at the very end of side 2, someone who is being interviewed about his application to [to] met, etc., or why I recorded it, I know not. But I'm sure if you want any of the talky sections of the tape obliterated, old Dan can do it for you. Hope you are well. It was good to see you and Vic here in SF. That mare of yours must have foaled by now!? Please advise. Love, Annie
      - "University of Arizona reading", Maxine Kumin, 1974 December 4; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248303)
      - Chas. T. Main, "Urban Engineering", 1971 February; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002091248295)
    - 10" and 12" Vinyl Sound Discs
      - Maxine Kumin. "Halfway", 1960; (2 sound discs) (Box 62 (Record Album Storage))
      - "Halfway (one lost poem)", 1960 July 7 (Box 62 (Record Album Storage))
    - Commercially Released Compact Discs
      - "The Writer's Almanac", 2004-2010; (13 compact discs) (Box 63)
      - "The Academy of American Poets. Larry Lewis", 1978 March 9 (Box 63)
      - "Poetry Alive!", 2000 (Box 63)
      - "New England College. Lectures & Readings by Faculty & Students", 2007 (Box 63)
      - "New England College. Faculty and Student Lectures", 2007; (2 compact discs) (Box 63)
      - Bruce Hoffman. "Welcome to Irony City", 2008 (Box 63)
- March 2013 Acquisition, 1945-1946; 3; (3 boxes)
  The March 2013 Acquisition consists of correspondence between Maxine and Victor Kumin, dating between 1945 and 1946, and photographs.
  Purchased from James S. Jaffe on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 2013.
  - Letters from Maxine Kumin to Victor Kumin, 1945-1946; 14 (Box 66)
  - Letters from Maxine Kumin to Victor Kumin, 1946; 5 (Box 67)
  - Letters from Victor Kumin to Maxine Kumin, 1945; 9 (Box 67)
  - Letters from Victor Kumin to Maxine Kumin, 1946; 10 (Box 68)
  - Photographs and negatives, undated; 1 folder (Box 68)